The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Our
guest speaker today
from Morgan Stanley,
Ivan Masyukov.
Dr. Ivan Masyukov.
IVAN MASYUKOV: Hello.
One, two, three.
Can you hear me?
PROFESSOR: And the microphone
will just be recording you,
but it doesn't broadcast you.
IVAN MASYUKOV: Ah.
Understood.
All right.
So I'm Ivan Masyukov.
I work in Morgan Stanley.
And my background is applied
physics and mathematics
from Moscow Institute of
Physics and Technology.
And today, the
topic of the lecture
is regularized pricing
and risk models.
So we will talk about
typical pricing risk
models for interest
rate products,
and the important
aspect of adding
some additional
constraints, which means,
like, adding some
regularizers to the model.
So we will start
from bonds, which
is probably the most
simple interest rate
product on the market.
Then we will discuss swaps.
We will build a yield curve.
And we will see how
yield curve models
can be improved to satisfy
needs of actual trader.
And at the end, we'll look
at the very nice example
of ill-posed problem
of calibrating
the two-dimensional
volatility surface
necessary for volatility model--
Monte Carlo assimilation.
And we will see how that
problem can be solved.
During the lecture, if
you have any questions,
please interrupt, OK?
So what is bond?
Bond is a security which
is issued if someone
like a borrower needs money.
And it promises to pay
some certain fixed amount
of certain cash
flows in the future,
and request for some
money up front for this.
So typical bonds basically
include same periodic payment--
let's say like every
half year or every year
until maturity, where at
maturity the face value is
paid, like the
biggest sum of money.
And again, during the
beginning, the investor
is asked to pay some up front.
There are also
zero-coupon bonds,
which don't pay anything
until the maturity.
And there are very
interesting perpetual bonds
where basically you pay
some money up front,
and then you pay it back
like infinitely-- which
sounds like a good
deal, but we will
know how to price it right.
So those are some diagrams.
So the first one is the
standard fixed-rate bond,
where small green arrows
represent a periodic payment.
And there is a face value added
on top of a periodic payment
at the maturity of the bond.
So this is a typical cash flow
diagram used for analysis, OK?
And so arrows up
represent something that--
and it's green right?
That is good for us.
So it's something
that we receive.
And a red arrow facing
down represents something
that you have to pay.
Right?
So a zero coupon bond is
something, as I said before,
is something that
you pay up front,
and you get back a fixed
amount of money in the future.
What's interesting
about this graph-- you
can see that the green
arrow has a bigger
amplitude than the red one,
which means that you kind
of, every time you put
like $100 now, right,
you kind of expect
that in return you
get more in the future.
Because if you don't
get more in the future,
you just don't get this
money, don't put this money.
You just keep it in the pocket.
So as a result, you get the
concept of time value of money.
So tomorrow, $100 always
will be more than just $100.
And also, if you look at the
graph of the fixed-rate coupon
bond, and you sum all
of the cash flows here,
it looks like you get
more than this red one.
But again, there is, as
further in the future
the cash flow is, the more
the kind of depreciation.
And we call this depreciation
a discount factor, OK?
So basically the more
in the future the cash
flow is, the smaller
the discount factor.
And so for today
the discount factor
will be 1, for tomorrow it will
be like 0.999, and so forth.
And in 30 years, let's say,
it will probably be like 0.1,
depending on current
rates in the market.
So let's see how we can
price the bond-- or not
necessarily price, but
compute a fair value
of future cash flows.
So our fair value of
computed cash flows
can be found if we
have discount factors.
So every discount factor
at every cash flow
in the future I-- which
in this particular case
will be a coupon
times the face value--
should be multiplied
by the discount factor.
And then we also add
a face value discount
with a discount factor at the
maturity of the instrument.
So the way this product
trades in the market
is that people buy and
sell bonds paying P, right?
So it's very important to
understand that for bonds, it's
not something that we have cash
flows which we kind of need
to price.
It's actually the
price is already known.
So it's very liquid.
It's the result of
activity in the market,
meaning that there is
very little uncertainty
about the price.
So this P is known.
And as with all cash flows,
it's something that's
written in the contract, right?
So it's something, we have
fixed cash flows in the future.
So it's always a question
about what kind of model
is useful for the
discount factors.
So we need a model
for discounting.
Any questions so far?
So one of the simplest models
is to use just one parameter
to kind of cover
all the discounting.
And the discount factor
can be represented
as e minus y times t
of i, t sub i, where
y is some kind of-- it's
called yield to maturity.
Well, the reason why
it's exponential,
it's natural right?
So if you have a 0.999
discount factor for today,
and then we kind
of say, OK, it's
the same discount
for tomorrow, we
will have the same discounting
for every other day.
So we have to multiply them.
As a result, the
total discounting
will be an exponential.
So if our discount
factors are like this,
then our price basically
can be represented
as a linear combination of
future cash flows, right?
At this point, by
the way, we kind of
merge together the final
coupon with the face value,
and we'll just kind of be
talking about the coupons
only, about cash flows only.
And so that's the formula
for the bond price, is this.
So basically, what's known
on the market is P, right,
which is a price that's--
that instrument is traded.
We also have defined
cash flows in the future.
So we can solve for the yield.
So essentially, if we
know the bond price,
we can find the bond yield, OK?
And if we know the bond yield,
we can find the bond price, OK?
So typically, bonds are
traded in terms of its price.
But some bonds are
traded in terms of yield.
But again, this is
like one-to-one.
You can always go
back and forth.
What's important is--
what has economic value,
right, is the bond price,
OK, and the future cash
amounts of cash flows.
And when you talk
about yield, it's
not something that's traded.
It's actually one of the ways
to align future cash flows
with the bond price.
And that way assumes
that we have,
again, constant discounting for
all time points in the future.
And we will see that it may
or may not be optimal case.
So what's also important when
we're talking about instrument
price is to have the model
of how that price changes
if the market changes.
So here, we're talking about
sensitivity of the bond price
to yield.
And what is typically
done is basically
to normalize by the
bond price itself.
And then it's called
bond duration.
So the nice thing
about normalizing
is that the duration
of that bond that you
have in your portfolio doesn't
really depend on how many bonds
you have, right?
So it's basically more like
property of the bond itself,
rather than how many bonds
you have in your portfolio.
So if you take the
previous formula
and take the derivative
with respect to y,
we get the following
formula for duration.
And we know what
the price is, right?
And we can rewrite
this formula this way,
which you see it's
a sum of t_i's times
some weights and divided
by the sum of the weights.
So it's essentially a
weighted sum of time, OK?
And those pieces of time,
those moments of time
is more important, as--
I mean the weights are
proportional to present
values of future cash flows.
So that's why bond duration
has a very nice kind
of intuitive sense.
As a result of that, and yeah,
I forgot to mention one thing.
So the duration is
always negative, right?
So we have a sign here, because
if the bond price goes up,
this means that the
yields goes down, OK?
And if the yield goes
up, price goes down.
And the explanation's
very simple.
So yield is kind
of the same thing
as interest rate on the market.
So if those rates
go up, this means
that there will be more
discounting in the future cash
flows, they will be
less valuable to me.
So I'll be less willing to
pay for those cash flows, OK?
So it's kind of fundamental
that relationship
has a negative sign.
So in case of a
zero-coupon bond,
we only have one cash
flow in the future.
So there is just one
weight, and that weight
is totally assigned to
that last cash flow.
So duration of zero-coupon
bond equals to maturity.
Duration of regular
coupon bond depends,
but it's always
less than maturity,
just because we'll have a
weighted sum formula here.
So essentially, that model
for the bond duration
kind of assumes that all rates--
so we have just one yield
number for everything,
so all rates go
like in a parallel way, which
was OK before the crisis,
right, where kind
of rates today are
kind of similar to the rates
expected in the future.
But it's no longer the case.
So the rates now, they're
higher than like one year ago,
but they're still much lower
than expected in the future.
So we expect that the
rates will go very high.
So the curve is very
steep at the moment.
So that model of just
one number for everything
might not be adequate.
And we'll see how we can
improve this situation.
So it's worth mentioning
the second derivative.
We already spoke
about the price,
first derivative of the
price with respect to yield,
and a second.
So for small changes
in the yield,
you can assume that
it's linear, so it's
OK to use just the
first derivative.
So second derivative will be
necessary for larger movements
of the market.
Like as an example, if you're
a trader, right, and the bond
trades, right?
So we call it a cash product.
Means that you actually don't
need any model to price it.
You already have that price, OK?
But if you try to explain like
why you might have lost money
today, right, and that
always-- the trader
always does that at
the end of the day.
And we always use
first derivatives.
And we try to explain it, but
there is also unexplained, OK?
And that unexplained
can be quite high
on this with large movements.
So if you have like a
term in your analytics
for the bond
convexity, that helps
you to include the
second derivative,
and therefore make the second
derivative smaller-- sorry--
the unexplained smaller.
So let's now talk about
interest rate swaps.
So bond cash flow is
basically a stream
of fixed cash flow, which
means that for certain dates
it's just guaranteed
that you will be getting
$100 with certain periodicity.
A swap means you
exchange fixed payments
with respect to some floating.
And floating means that the
amount of money that you'll
be getting or paying,
OK, receiving or paying,
will depend on some
market observable.
So for interest rate swap, it
will be typically-- and let's
focus on the USD market, it will
be a three month LIBOR rate.
That rate is
published daily, OK?
And it's like if you
need to go to the bank
and get a three month CD with
the money for the three months,
that rate is already known.
It's actually called
LIBOR, because it's
kind of between banks, and
it's set at 11 AM London time.
So as a result, we
already know how
to price cash flows
in the future.
So present value of the fixed
stream of payments, as we know,
will be like this.
And there is a floating
rate of cash flow as well.
And the nice thing
about the swap
is that when you enter the swap,
you don't pay any money, right?
It's because you just kind
of enter the agreement,
rather than when you
buy or sell a bond,
there is some exchange of money.
For swaps, swaps are
designed the way such
that-- so when you
make this agreement,
it's a certain moment of time,
the fixed rate of the swap
is picked in such a way
that the present value
of fixed minus the floating
cash flows will be net to zero.
So you can see, I mean, if
we rewrite those equations,
OK, we can see that
the swap rate-- which
is the most important
quantity of the swap,
and something that
traders are basically
are most concerned, right?
So you first need to
define what the swap is.
And for USD, you are saying
probably like 10 year swap, OK.
And this is the rate.
So the trader continuously kind
of quotes bid and offer levels
of the swap rate.
So no one is talking about
PVs and stuff like that.
So it's always the swap rate.
So that the swap rate is a
weighted sum of forward rates.
And it has a very nice
intuitive explanation.
So you have some stream
of floating cash flows--
variable cash flows--
which at the moment, like,
will probably be low now,
but will be high in 10 years,
will be much higher in 30 years.
So the swap rate for
this kind of environment
will be kind of
an average, right?
And again, those weights depend
on the discounting factors.
So later, we will see
that because we're
talking about bond that
having a fixed cash
flows in the futures, and a
swap that fixed in exchange
of floating, swap can be hedged
with bond, "hedged" meaning
that-- you know what the
term "hedged" means, no?
Hedging means that if you have
just, let's say, a swap, right?
So if market changes, right,
you can again lose money.
So a typical task
for the money-maker,
trader, is to kind of offset
that risk with something.
Ideally, you sold
one swap, you bought
another swap the same way
with a different rate.
So you kind of locked
in your profit.
But you remain with a zero risk.
So let's try to
construct a yield curve.
Why do we need the yield curve?
So when we have,
let's say, a series
of swap with different
maturities, right,
all those swaps
will start today,
and usually, swap will
have quarterly payment
for the floating leg, and six
month payments for the fixed
leg, and you'll have
different maturities.
But if you try to kind
of get discount factors
from that information,
you will see
that you can get those discount
factors only for certain dates,
OK?
But the typical
situation is that given
on some liquid
market instruments,
you want to price your
entire portfolio, which
has continuous
spectrum of cash flows
from now to 30 years, 40 years.
And also, for typical
swap portfolio
that I personally deal
with on a daily basis
contains hundreds of
thousands of swaps.
Every swap has many cash flows.
So you need something
that can, based
on discrete information of
reliable liquid instruments
on the market, draw the line.
Can basically
construct the curve.
Which means that
you can, so that you
are able to get discount
factors for any potential day
in the future, or you
can compute forward rate
for every date in the future.
So the first step to
construct a yield curve
is to select input
instruments for calibration.
So you have a set
of instruments,
and a new set of input quotes.
Then you also need
to kind of decide
what kind of properties
of that line will be.
So you can say,
OK, first of all,
you need to decide what
quantity will be interpolated.
It could be daily
discount factors,
or daily forward rates, or
maybe three-month forward rates.
Then you select the spline type.
So I'm not sure if you're
familiar with the splines.
Probably you heard about
cubic spline, right?
So there are different types
of splines, and some of them
are better and some of them are
worse for different situation.
And you also need
to decide like what
that will be the node points
for the spline itself.
OK.
And then, as a
final step, so you
have some mathematical
quantity, which
is mathematical object where
you know what the line is,
and you have control points.
And you need to adjust
your control points such
that when you reprice
your instruments,
those instruments are repriced
exactly to the same quotes
that you find on the market.
You have a question.
AUDIENCE: Is that spline,
again, is it just like a--
IVAN MASYUKOV: All right.
So let me.
All right.
So this is a picture
of the cubic spline.
So spline is a way to
draw a smooth curve.
This is an example
of the cubic spline.
So you start to define
your node points.
Your node points in this
case are 1, 10, 20, 40,
80, 160, and 240, right?
And then for every one
of those intervals,
OK, the functional form
of the shape of this curve
is a cubic polynomial, OK?
Well, if you just do cubic
polynomial for every interval
without kind of putting
additional constraints,
you can have all kinds of
boundary effects, like jumps,
kinks, and other things, because
we want our cubic curve--
cubic spline-- to be
meaningful, right?
So we want to
maintain, to preserve
maximum number of derivatives
for every node point.
So we're not going to check.
But believe me,
this curve, it is
a cubic polynomial for
every one of those interval.
And also, we have two continuous
derivative at every node point,
because for the n
degree of the spline,
you always have like n minus 1.
You can have n minus 1.
So the same thing, a
spline can be represented
in terms of B-splines.
B-spline is a new
type of spline.
It's just as a representation
which is more intuitive,
I should say.
So all universe of the curves
with those node points,
with two continuous
derivatives, can
be represented as a linear
combination of those basis
functions.
So B-spline, I mean,
if you're interested,
you should probably, we're not
going to discuss it in details,
but it's nice separate
kind of topic about how
to build those B-splines.
But essentially, what's
nice about those B-splines--
and "B," as you probably already
understood, B is basis, right?
So you have like
basis functions.
So those functions
look like bell shapes.
They are non-zero on
some sub-interval.
On every interval, it will
be a cubic polynomial.
Everyone will have always
two continuous derivatives.
As a result, in any
linear combination
of those-- which
the first curve is--
will also have that property.
OK.
So now we, yeah,
so the calibrate
means that we basically
have some solver
to make sure that our swaps with
the rates for those maturities
actually repriced at par.
At par means that
the PV is zero.
This is a typical example of
the yield curve instruments.
And IRS stands for
"interest rate swap,"
and we have maturities
from one year to 30 years.
And the quotes are
of 0.33% up to 2.67%.
So you can see that
that's actually,
that's from my
one-year-old presentation.
Rates are quite high these days.
So this is an example of
the yield curve graph.
So again, so those are
the rates from 0.3 to 3.5.
And the shape of the curve
is not flat at all, right?
So it's actually pretty steep.
So for the first five
years, it's very steep.
Then it reaches the plateau.
And then there is
some feature there,
probably because of some
behavior in the 20-year region.
So three-month forward
rate is the LIBOR rate.
LIBOR is the rate
for the three month.
It's mostly kind of common.
And the reason why is because
the standard interest rate,
USD swap has a
three-month frequency
for payment on the floating leg.
So if you're talking
about floating rates,
is always three months.
And it's always LIBOR.
So because we've
already built the curve,
now let's see how we can improve
the situation with a bond.
So we have the curve, so we have
the discount factors, right?
And we see that those discount
factors cannot be obtained
on the assumption that you
have just one parameter yield
for everything, because the
curve we know is not flat.
So if we just try to price it
using those discount factors,
try to get a fair
price, we probably
won't match the
market observables.
So we need some extra term.
And again, here we can
use it in a similar form
as we did it for the yield.
But right now it's going to be
a small correction to the yield
curve, rather than kind
of really rough assumption
about that the
curve is flat, OK?
So typically, if the curve
magnitude is, let's say, 3%.
OK?
So the spread is
probably 100 times lower.
So having a nice correction
is always better, right?
And another nice feature is that
of this approach for the bond,
like if we already build
our yield curve model,
and we know sensitivities
of our portfolio
to inputs of the curves,
which then transition
into like differences
in discount factors,
we can easily apply
that to the bond.
We can first find what
this spread parameter
is, to solve for s knowing P,
which is very liquid market
tradable.
And then we can kind of use
consistent model for the bonds
and the swaps in our portfolio.
Any questions?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
So what does the bond rate
tell us about the bond?
IVAN MASYUKOV: That's
a very good question.
So it might tell us something
like bond liquidity,
for example.
Like if it's not
liquid, or there
is some-- so it may be
related to the bond itself.
And sometimes we kind
of think that the bond
is riskless, which means
that-- especially if it's
issued by US government,
which if we can assume
that those cash flows in the
futures are guaranteed, right,
then I basically will
be willing to bring
a certain amount of money
and discount factors, right?
But if you tell me that you
will pay me that in the future,
I won't be so certain, right?
So I'll need to add some
kind of credit spread
to that-- we call it credit
spreads-- as a result.
It's the credit spread will
kind of propagate to the spread
number.
On the other hand, if the bond
is really US government-issued,
and is considered
to be guaranteed,
then it may be a
feature of the swap, OK?
Where just because of
some liquidity situations
in swap market--
like all of a sudden,
let's say, all option
traders on the street
needed this 10-year swap, OK?
Because they kind of need to
hedge certain very popular
products-- volatility products--
they'll start to buy it,
that spread will change.
But what's even
more interesting,
that spread is
tradable by itself, OK?
So you can go to the market
and you trade the spread.
Moreover, let's look,
like, 10-year situation.
So you have 10-year
bond on the market.
You have tradable swap, and
you have tradable spread.
So the question is which
one is the most liquid?
What do you think?
The most liquid is
the bond, of course.
It has much more liquidity.
Surprisingly, the second one.
It's the spread between
the 10-year swap
and the bond is
traded in the market.
So there's more
transaction on the spread
rather compared to the swap.
As a result, when
we built our curves,
we're not taking like
10-year swap from the market.
OK.
We actually take the
yield and the spread.
And that's how we
define the most kind
of reliable level of the swap.
Of course, we could
have just take
whatever we observe
for the 10-year swap,
but it could be off.
And also, if you observe, there
will be more bid-offer spread
as well.
So as an example,
let's try to shift
one of the inputs of the
curve by one basis point.
And that will result in
this kind of deviation
of forward trades, which will
be combination of basis splines.
But what's interesting
first of all,
it's kind of complicated
[INAUDIBLE] behavior.
The reason why is because you
are saying that nothing changed
before the nine
year, like nothing
changed after ninth year,
but just point in between.
So in order to calibrate to
that kind of weird condition,
right, you need to
have a ripple here.
But what also is more important
is that by shifting one year
basis point by one basis
point, that the amplitude
of shifts in the curve
reaches 14 basis points.
So not sure if you're familiar,
but it's an ill-posed problem
right?
So small changes in your inputs
can cause large variations
in your outputs.
This is a very important slide.
So the first column
is, again, we
saw those are our
instruments, quotes,
and this is the risk
of the portfolio.
That's something that a
trader needs no matter what.
It basically shows
you what happens
on the market if
different-- what
will be the change
in your portfolio
if the market changes.
So the meaning of the number--
for example, for the five
year-- is that if five year rate
moves up by one basis point,
we'll lose minus 700K.
We also marked
here yellow points
that are more liquid
than the others.
So now a typical
situation is that you need
to hedge your portfolio, right?
So you need to liquidate your
risk, I'm basically saying,
OK, given the
model that we have,
I want its value to be
insensitive to any movements
on the market.
So for that purpose, what
you can do, you can go
and you can buy as many
one-year swaps as plus 200,
as many two-year swaps which
would be the risk of minus 1.3,
and so forth, right?
Then that always
cost you money right?
And that money is kind of
proportional to bid-offer
of the particular instruments.
And that bid-offer is smaller
for liquid instruments
and larger for less
liquid instruments.
So if you multiply
by the diff-- we
can see that if we
want to hedge our risk,
it's going to be
quite expensive.
It will cost us 3.6
million dollars.
Any questions so far?
So traders never hedge
every bucket in the risk.
Bucket means every line here.
So you always see some
numbers, but if you
try to make every
number here zero,
which means that if
you trade seven here,
you also could try
to go to the market,
find the offsetting seven here,
you'll have to pay too much
and you won't be profitable.
So what the traders do if
someone ask for the seven year,
they make this transaction,
but they go, then
hedge it from the more
liquid points, which
is less expensive to buy.
So we need a better
model for hedging.
And a general formulation of
the model is presented here.
So we have portfolio risk which
is a just the vector here,
right?
And we have hedging.
Portfolio risk is basically
if you have candidates
of instruments that you can use
for portfolio hedging, again,
the risk will be represented
in this format in terms
of sensitivities to swap rates.
And we have weights of
that hedging portfolio
that we need to find, obviously.
So you have this
hedging portfolio.
You multiply H by x, you get
risk of this hedging portfolio.
You add it to the risk
of your portfolio.
And then, what we
need to minimize,
you don't need to
minimize everything.
But you need to if
they give you, OK?
What can happen on the market?
What are the typical
modes of the market?
And so essentially you
kind of define your market
scenarios, which can be
found in a different way.
So one of the ways to
approach that problem
is to use principal
component analysis.
I know you already
are familiar with SVD.
So if D is data of market
movements in matrix--
then any matrix can be
decomposed using SVD.
And we can then look at this
spectrum of this decomposition,
looking at those
eigenvalues, and just
pick the ones that look
high enough for us,
and just keep that number.
And let's, for example, we find
that we really investigated
this market, and we
found that there are just
five components that
drive the market,
and the rest is just so little
that it's meaningless, right?
On every day, and we are
certain that it's just
five components, five
modes of market moments.
Then, if we have a curve
that consists of 20 points,
we don't need to
hedge every swap
with its corresponding maturity.
We can just pick
five swaps that are
liquid enough and
cheap enough for us
to hedge, and just use them.
So let's look now at
those typical graphs
of those principal components.
X-axis is the swap
maturity in years,
and y is some kind of
relative, let's think
of that as basis points.
So blue line is
the first component
which is the prevalent.
And it kind of, you can
see that swap rates,
they're basically
flattish after 10 years,
but the first component
is pretty steep.
And what it says as well is that
the main behavior of the market
is that rates now do
not move, but they
will move in the future.
And that's basically because
Fed is in a hold, right?
So they kind of stimulate
the market in a way such
that the rate remains the same
until sometime in the future.
Mode number two is a kind
of like tilting situation.
Mode number three
is more complex.
And we'll have several
other modes here as well.
So now, following our
previous general approach
to the problem,
we formulated here
as-- so we have PCA
factors here in P.
And now, because the number
of factors that we selected
is the number of
hedging instruments--
we no longer need to minimize.
We can always feed, which
you can always achieve
like perfect minimization.
We can always achieve that zero.
So that's why we
formulate it as zero.
So solving that problem here.
Yeah.
And the hedging matrix, this is
an example of hedging matrix.
So what that matrix says is
that if I take one year swap
and put in my portfolio,
empty portfolio,
and then they apply my model,
I'll have just sensitivity
to that particular swap.
Which kind of makes
sense, because since you
use the same instruments to
calibrate your yield curve,
right, then it should be
sensitive to itself only.
That's why that matrix
is just ones for itself,
and zeroes otherwise.
So then, as a result,
we get this matrix.
So same portfolio
that we had before.
This is our PCA matrix
that translates our risk
into those few numbers, right?
And because we know it
translates our risk-- low risk,
in terms of many curve
inputs-- into just five most
liquid ones, which is
1, 2, 5, 10, and 30.
As a result, our
translated risk,
which tells us what we need
to do to hedge our portfolio,
is just those numbers.
And now, if we take a
bid-offer charge, 0.1 basis
points for those,
and multiply, we
get numbers which are
orders of magnitude
smaller than we
got before, right?
So we probably get something
like there were 400.
It's not 4 million--
3.6 million anymore.
That's exactly what traders do.
And different traders
have different opinions
of what dynamics
of the market is.
But they always have some model.
So disadvantages.
So PCA model is something
that just formally attuned
to historical data.
I always say that if you take
kind of scramble your swap
maturities in your model,
and you do your computations,
and you kind of
unscramble them, you
get exactly the same result.
Which means that in PCA model,
you don't put any
constraints on that.
Two year is very
close to one year,
and two year is between
one year and five year.
So PCA model or hedging
coefficients of that matrix
is not very stable-- especially
for recent modes in the market.
Also, because SVDs kind
of is the least squares
approximation, it's very
sensitive to outliers.
So there is just one event on
the market that kind of one day
happens, something
like rates went up,
and then it went
down significantly,
it may have unnecessarily
high influence on the outputs.
And if those coefficients
change daily,
right, then again,
it may be too costly.
And quite often we just
overfitting to historical data.
So we're saying,
OK, what can I do.
I just take
historical data, and I
prove that my model works, would
have worked for the last three
years, or the last
three months, but that
doesn't mean that it will work
for the next three months.
If we kind of try to put
some additional constraints
or additional thoughts about
what this behavior should be,
this may improve situation.
So PCA interpretation
is that risk matrix
is a linear combination of
principal components producing
a shift on one hedging
instrument at a time.
Now the question is, let's
forget about historical, OK?
Is there any other approach?
We know historical is noisy,
and it's kind of first step
if you want to build the model.
But can we do something better?
And the answer is yes.
So we can say that we
have our yield curve
in terms of forward rates.
And typically, when
we build this curve,
we observe that it is smooth.
It's smooth not only because
we use smooth splines,
but also because if there is
no certainty about some event
in 10 years from now, there
is no reason to kind of expect
there will be spike or
some non-smooth feature
in the forward rate space.
So what we can do
is that we can try
to minimize those
equations where Jacobian
is a matrix translating
shifts of yield curve inputs
into movements of
forward trades.
So essentially, we will try
to penalize non-smoothness.
And the solution
will be like this,
with some kind of-- so we'll
be adding a penalty, OK.
And penalty will be a small
regularization parameter.
So this is, as an example,
that's what we get.
Again, here in that model.
You can view this matrix
as if one year rate moves,
what it basically-- so your
drivers are 1, 2, 5, 10s,
and 30s.
So that's your drivers.
Knowing the movements
of your drivers,
what would be the response
to your swap rates?
And you know that it will
always be one to itself,
right, as you see here.
And in between, it will be
kind of a smooth functions.
So let's take, this
moment, a broader view
at what the pricing model does.
And we have a pricing
engine, essentially.
It's a way, if you have all
model parameters-- including
curves, volatility, the
surface, everything, right?
And in order for
those parameters
to be consistent with
the benchmark prices,
you need some
calibration engine which
matches market observables
to the ones that's
been repriced by the model
output of the pricing engine.
And once you make sure that
benchmark prices of your model
equal or are kind of close
enough to benchmark prices
observed in the market,
you calibrated the model,
then you can essentially
price your portfolio,
and get values and risk.
So let's look at one of
the nice examples of how
that pricing engine and pricing
and calibration process works.
We'll look at HJM model, which
is used to price volatility
products.
So we're not going to go into
too many details about this,
but this is equations of
evolution of forward rates
that we need for simulation,
for Monte Carlo simulation.
What we're saying here is this
change of the forward rates--
because forward rates
is the quantity that
is being assimilated--
has some drift, OK?
Because dt is time.
And also, it has some
dependence on the forward rates
to the power of beta, right?
So if it's log-normal
model, beta will be one.
If it's normal model,
beta will be zero.
But in general, it's different.
Then we have volatility
surface, right,
which kind of gives you what
the number of volatility
to use for this calendar
and forward time.
And we have correlation and
factor structure which we're
not going to talk about here.
And this is Brownian motions.
So we're not going to go
any more complex like this.
We'll just start looking at
nice, two-dimensional surfaces
here, and see what are the
problems of calibrating
the volatility surface.
Just to give you
a diagram of when
we look at the surface,
what different elements
of that surface mean.
It's a triangular surface.
You have a calendar time, right,
and you have a forward time.
So your simulation starts
at the first vertical line.
So you have forward
rates here as calibrated
from the curve as of today.
So those are square boxes
here, square elements.
So you need to
kind of transition
from the first line
to the second step
using Monte Carlo simulation.
And that's when, for
every arrow here,
you need the volatility number.
Then, once you did
your Monte Carlo
simulation for the
second one, you
need ones for the third one.
And again you need data--
which volatility to use, OK?
So essentially, the
surface that we'll
be looking at on next
slides is essentially
representing the numbers
necessary for this transition's
volatility for every arrow.
So to explain, there are
different areas here.
Like, for example, those will
be-- if one step is one here,
OK, we're talking about this, it
will be the forward rates that
will be observed in two years.
That one will be observed as of
now for like one year from now.
But again, in two years.
And so those rates are
essential to compute the swap,
forward swap rate.
And if we do our Monte
Carlo simulation,
that's essential
information that we
need to compute the
price for the option
on the swap, which we're
not going to discuss here.
But just an example, it shows
that for different instruments
observed in the market
you have quite overlapping
areas of sensitivity.
So this is a typical example
of the volatility surface
where this is calendar
time, this is forward time.
And it has spikes
for certain regions.
But in general, it's smooth.
So why this problem
is challenging.
If we try to compute the
triangle matrix, which
has dimension of 240 by
240-- the reason why is 240
is because every element
is for three months, OK?
But we need up to
60 years of data,
which means that
it's 60 by 4, which
is the number of
quarters, is 240 by 240.
If you just need triangle
elements, it's 200K elements.
So if you try to calibrate
everything at the same time,
and you formally try
to solve your problem,
you kind of needed to store, at
least to build a matrix of 28K
by 28K.
And we just don't
have memory for this.
And we also have
very small number
of calibration instruments only
in terms of swaptions or caps,
which are typical
volatility products.
We just have a
relatively small number.
So it's an
underdetermined problem.
We also, as we saw on
the previous example,
areas of sensitivity of
different instruments overlap.
And it's an ill-posed
inverse problems which
produces unstable solutions.
And no matter what we do,
right, the resulting surface
should be nice, right?
Should look nice, right?
Because if it has spikes in
some points in the future, then
we either have an
economic reason for this,
or we claim that this is
something that's not realistic.
So this is how we
approach the problem.
So the first step, we represent
our volatility surface.
And here, even though volatility
surface is two-dimensional
we just kind of assign a number
for every of those elements,
OK, and then represent the
surface as a vector, OK?
Whereas saying that
the new surface v
will be some initial state
plus a linear combination
of basis functions.
And basis functions
should correspond
to some reasonable
functions, OK?
But the nice feature is that
number of basis functions
will be much smaller than
the number of elements
that we need to calibrate.
But we will be very formal here.
And we'll try to use same
number of basis functions
as we have our
input instruments.
So in case we had 50
input instruments,
we select basis functions
also the number 50.
So we will use typical
Newton-Raphson approach here.
We will compute sensitivities
of input of all instruments
to perturbations of a
volatility surface, OK?
We'll build this
Jacobian matrix.
And then, if we made the
reasonable assumptions
about what those
basis functions are,
then we can invert
our square Jacobian.
And again, the reason
why it's square
is because we selected same
number of basis functions
as the number of
input instruments.
It's actually quite
common approach,
but it's very often
is wrong approach.
It produces unstable results.
And we will see why.
So we converge to
exact solution,
but now the volatility
surface looks like this.
It looks less like a
volatility surface,
but more like Manhattan skyline.
So you have a Hudson
River here, and you
have some buildings right?
Obviously, even though it
calibrates exactly, right?
And you could go and
price your portfolio,
but probably prices
for instruments
in the portfolio
that are not input
instruments for calibration
would be meaningless.
Because the reason why we
need this surface to be smooth
is because for
similar instruments
for similar products
in your portfolio
you kind of expect
similar prices, right?
So if your volatility
jumps, that's
something that just contradicts
with this assumption.
So now how can we
improve the situation?
So we can try to use our
basis functions which
were selected in terms of
piecewise constant shift
of different areas.
We can use a smooth
version of those plans.
But again, the result
looks better, but still
is not good enough.
And just to demonstrate that
this is an ill-posed problem--
an ill-posed
problem is something
that small changes
of your inputs
results in insane
changes in your output.
And this is a typical example.
So keep all the
instruments the same, OK?
We just change by 1%--
which is not a big number--
of the five year by
10 year swaption,
results in a quite large change
of the volatility surface.
But look also at
the shape right?
So it's really kind of
you look at one building
with an antenna, and
another building, right?
So it's very unreasonable change
of the volatility surface.
So we can use ill-posedness
to our advantage.
So basically, at
this point we say,
well, it's not a requirement
to calibrate exactly,
just because every
instruments that
is an input of collaboration
actually has some tolerance.
So even there is no point
to calibrate it exactly.
So because we know that
small variations in inputs
can be large
variations of outputs,
we can put some
constraints on the outputs.
And actually, that
may not cost us
much in terms of not being
able to calibrate exactly,
but produce much more
meaningful result.
And just to be absolutely
sure that our output
result, our surface
is smooth, we
can use basis functions that
are smooth to begin with.
So we'll use B-splines, but
those will be two-dimensional.
And we'll talk a little
bit more about this.
And it's not a requirement
for us to have as many basis
functions as we have
instruments, because we
can put some other constraints.
Like, for example, we can
put smoothness or gradient
smoothness to the surface.
So let's pick some relatively
high but reasonable number
of functions-- could be more
than the number of input
instruments-- and
see what we can do.
So first of all,
let's build our basis
functions for the surface.
So this slide we
already just saw,
that we selected to
use B-splines, which is
very convenient to work with.
This is a one-dimensional.
This is the way we
build them, typically.
So we use the Cox-de
Boor recursion formula.
You start from linear, right?
Then you apply that formula.
You transition to the basis
set of the second order.
And then the next iteration,
you have the third order.
And those ones will be built.
So now, if you take those basis
functions in one dimension,
and same basis functions
in the other dimension,
and then you compute the
kind of 10s of products,
like you multiply
them one by one,
then you get basis functions
with shapes like this.
Which means that no
matter what we do, right,
like, because every basis
function makes sense,
then any linear combinations
will also be good enough.
So to formulate the
problem is very simple.
So we're saying, OK, the
quotes produced by our model
should be close enough to
what's observed in the market,
with some weights again.
But we don't require
any more that those
are calibrated exactly.
We are going to put some
penalty function to the change
of the volatility surface.
And we're going to put
some penalty function
to the volatility
surface itself.
So those are vectors, right?
And L_1 and L_2 are matrices.
So just to give you an example
what those matrices should be,
like if you are talking
about smoothness,
if you want to penalize the
gradient of the vector, right,
then the matrix will
consist of rows of one
and following minus 1.
So what you're
saying, OK, if I want
to penalize the difference
between this and the next.
And you do that for
every element, OK?
And the penalty kind of consists
of all penalties that you have.
So here we just formulate
our problem right?
So we want once-- because we've
had the Jacobian-- we want
to price things close enough.
And there are two
penalty terms here
with the different
regularization parameters.
So once we have this, we can
just, using linear algebra,
the solution is defined here.
And this is resulting
calibration, which
we see is nice and smooth.
So if we take the analysis
of the calibration inverse
problem, let's do that
using our linear algebra
tools to understand where
the problem is coming from.
OK, so A is a matrix,
translates our model parameters
to market observables.
And there is some error
there-- epsilon, OK?
So you can see
that your solution
is a linear combination
of singular values divided
by the singular values, OK?
So if your values are high,
OK, then that's not a problem.
The problem is that once you get
very small singular values, OK,
the deviation of
v_i's can result
in the large deviation of
your reconstructed result.
And that's when
you have a problem.
So this is described
on this slide.
So "ill-posed" is that small
noise may be significantly
amplified by small
singular values.
And if you have a problem when
you don't know how good it is,
and whether you can
trust it or not,
so it's a very
standard approach,
you compute the
condition number,
which is the ratio of the
maximum to minimum singular
values.
And if the number
is high, which means
that there are some
very insignificant modes
in your input data that can
cause substantial changes
in your output.
And if you know that,
it's not comforting right?
So if that mode actually
doesn't present in reality,
then that's fine.
But there is no
guarantee, right?
See, if that happens, then
your model basically blows up.
And that slide displays exactly
that noiseless situation,
where it looks like if
you don't have any noise
and if your model
is perfect, then
you're always able
to calibrate exactly
to the market observables.
But it's never the case right?
So there's always
uncertainty to the numbers
that you're calibrating to.
And your model is
not always perfect.
So very standard technique
for that particular problem
is the Tikhonov
regularization, which,
when you solve your
ill-posed problem, as trying
to minimize x minus y, you add
some penalty to the amplitude
to your solution.
Which essentially
saying, OK, give me
something reasonable, but
something that's not blown-up.
If you go through
this linear algebra,
to see how that lambda parameter
in the Tikhonov regularization
affects the weights of the
SVD kind of representation
of your solution, we now see
that small singular values
is no longer a problem,
just because we're not
dividing by the small
number, but actually we
are kind of limited by some
regularization parameter.
And typically, when you
apply that regularization,
your model no longer gives
you a perfect match, right?
But the result is much more
meaningful, and more stable.
Another approach
to the problem is--
and before we go to that slide.
So kind of Tikhonov
regularization we
used for surface calibration.
Here, a standard
Tikhonov regularization
is something that
you just penalize
the amplitude of
the solution itself.
But it doesn't have to be the
amplitude of the solution.
It can be some linear
combination of your solution.
And in terms of calibrating
of volatility surface,
we didn't apply penalty to
the reconstructed volatility,
but we say it's not that the
amplitude of the solution
that we don't like.
We don't like non-smoothness.
So let's penalize the
derivatives of the surface
in the different angles.
Another approach would be to
use a truncated SVD, where
we say, OK, so we did our
singular value decomposition.
We're looking at the
spectrum of singular values,
and we find that some numbers
look nice and large, some very
small.
And then we just
skip the small ones.
It's very similar to the
PCA approach for the risk
management that we
saw before, where
we just selected five
principal components
and we ignored the rest.
As a result, the model
is much more robust.
And by doing this,
we essentially
truncate the null
space of the model.
If you're familiar
with this, it's
basically the space that has
very small singular values.
So what regularized models gives
you is that improved stability.
It's absolutely essential
for ill-conditioned problems.
And it's a more realistic
and meaningful result
at the expense of some beauty
to fit exactly the data,
but that's something that
is quite often acceptable.
It might cause a
biased solution,
meaning that your solution
again may not be exact.
It might be biased towards
some better result.
For example, if you apply
smoothness constraint,
the solution would kind
of assume a little bit
more smooth result
than it actually is.
But that's acceptable.
And the bias, again,
can be minimized
by reasonable selection of
what quantity you actually
don't like.
Again, you can say,
oh, during calibration
of our volatilities of our
surface we could have said,
you know what?
Let's just open the textbook and
see what's the regularization.
OK, we find Tikhonov.
We start to penalize
the amplitude.
Then the result won't be good.
So we need to think
about and say, OK,
what exactly we don't like.
Like, for example, is like
absolutely flat volatility
surface good for us?
And we'll find, yeah,
that that's actually fine.
Then, if we said that then
penalizing the amplitude
doesn't make sense,
so we need to penalize
something that is a deviation
from that perfect flat
solution.
Or to be more kind
of precise, we
penalize like the derivative
in different directions.
So this kind of concludes
my presentation today.
And there are some
useful links if you
want to get more information.
Thank you.
Any question?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
So regarding the techniques
that you use for fitting
function that you are
using spline techniques.
What other techniques--
is the spline
the best technique you use?
IVAN MASYUKOV: Well,
spline is, yes.
So a spline or
interpolation is the same.
So we're always talking
about interpolation.
So you have some limited
number of inputs,
and you want to draw in between.
So there are just
two words for this,
which is a interpolation-- or
spline-- which I consider to be
the same thing in general.
AUDIENCE: I have a question
about the interpolation graph
that you had where the
following was very smooth.
When you, as an expert in
this, look at that graph
and see, I guess,
just some odd shapes
at certain parts of the curve,
how do you interpret that?
And do you assess that that's
a feature of the current term
market liquidity conditions, or
possibly just a mathematical--
IVAN MASYUKOV:
Well, first of all,
I mean, that grid is done
like for-- every element is
a three-month.
But what's traded on the market?
Like, typical maturities
are three-month,
maybe half-year, one year,
two year, five year, 10 year.
So we should kind of rescale
it in a logarithmic scale,
or-- you know what
I'm talking about?
And then, if you do
that, then this peak
doesn't look a peak anymore.
So the reason why it looks
like a feature to you
is because it's quite
sharper than this guy, right?
But that's because you have many
more detailed instruments there
compared to here.
And that's the reason why we
selected our basis functions
like this.
So we selected more node
density in the front,
just because there are more
instruments in the front
than at the end.
So we want our spline to be
more detailed at the beginning,
and kind of just nice
and smooth at the end.
So that's why those basis
functions-- which correspond
very well to actual instruments
that we have in the portfolio--
can produce, first of all, you
see this spike here too, right?
So is it like you can
compare this guy to this guy.
But essentially, it's just
they have similar magnitude,
but we don't have enough
instruments in this area
to support any sharper features.
So I don't see any
problems with this graph.
But traders, because they
look at this every day, right?
And then they calibrate,
and they see a feature,
and then they immediately
kind of trying to think.
OK, if you see something that
you know is not typical--
and that sense of
typical/not typical
comes with years of
experience-- then they
try to arbitrage this.
Because if there is a
spike in the surface,
it's very likely that
it will disappear soon.
AUDIENCE: So if
this is the model
for volatility, that's used in
modeling for swaptions, right?
IVAN MASYUKOV: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: So if you
were to actually try
to go about making a trade
out of some discrepancy
that you see, can you
kind of describe how
you'd do that with swaption?
Do you use basically
like regular options?
IVAN MASYUKOV: I don't
have the screen here.
But essentially what
traders do, right?
So this is, I mean that
calibrator we actually use.
And it's a real-time calibrator.
The reason why it
can be real time
is because there is just
simple linear algebra there.
Most of stuff like A transpose
A can be pre-calculated.
So it can be real time.
So they can see this
volatility surface
moving while-- we connect
to actual market data.
And once they see there
is anomaly on the market,
there is something traded
which they believe is wrong,
OK, they're just make
an advantage of that.
They just make a trade, that
would be swaption, for example,
or maybe some other trade
more exotic than swaptions.
But again, having
like the dependence
on the particular instruments,
which kind of would
express your position
that this will change
like in a day or so.
So that's exactly how
the desk makes money.
So we call it relative
value analysis.
So if we have a tool like
that, you have a model.
You have your input instruments,
and you have some regularizing
terms of it could
be smoothness, it
could be a PCA, it could be
combination of PCA, right?
But then that
additional information
allows you to find
anomalies in the market.
Once you find those
anomalies, you
can take advantage of them--
provided that your model is
robust enough.
And if you are saying, well,
I am kind of doing well,
and I'm calibrate well with
just some smoothness assumption
about smoothness of
the forward rates,
there is nothing more
fundamental than this.
So if your model is based
on fundamental principle,
you can expect that it will
be more stable in the future,
rather than PCA.
Because for PCA, you
just kind of say,
OK, I took the time interval.
I kind of did my regression
analysis, whatever.
But that doesn't mean that
the market will continue
to do the same in the future.
AUDIENCE: I have a question.
[INAUDIBLE] marketer.
And then we would try to price
the bond at that premium.
You mentioned that actually bond
is the most liquid instrument
in the market.
So why not you do the area
around by inverse bond
to derive the discounting
factor from a bond [INAUDIBLE].
IVAN MASYUKOV: Well, that's
a very good question.
So basically we could
have done that, OK.
And some firms do that.
The problem is
that with swaps, we
kind of have those swaps
today, they kind of
roll every day, OK?
They like, the swap today
starts today, swap tomorrow
starts tomorrow,
things like that.
But bonds do not.
OK so they basically, there
is like on-the-run bond, which
is the most liquid one, which
once the new ten-year bond is
issued, then that bond
becomes off-the-run.
It's still traded,
but then everyone
switches to on-the-run.
So you don't have a nice
continuous spectrum of bonds.
You have kind of concentrations
between on-the-runs
and off-the-runs.
And if you want to draw
the curve for all of them,
you typically cannot
do the perfect fit.
You kind of need to
do the least squares.
So it's just more convenient
to do it in the swap.
But once we build the swap
curve, swap trader typically--
I should say always
use bonds for hedging,
just because bonds
are much more liquid.
Then we project bonds
to the swap curve
rather than swaps to the bond
curve, which is hard to build.
AUDIENCE: So in
this case, when they
switch from on-the-run,
off-the-run, [INAUDIBLE]?
IVAN MASYUKOV: Yes.
So your curve won't be stable,
just because those roll
effects-- we call
those "roll effects"--
which means that there is
something substantial changes
on the market.
And there may be
such a big demand
for this new bond on the market,
that will make your curve, that
won't look nice.
So there are also traders
that just trade bonds.
And those typically
don't have curves.
They rely on some PCA
models, or some other things.
PROFESSOR: Thanks again.
IVAN MASYUKOV: Thank you.